Okay, so in this video then, we are going
to discuss two earned value formulas,
right, called Schedule Variance and Cost
Variance, our SV and CV.
Now, the scenario that we're looking at is
basically this scenario here, right,
we're five weeks into a 10-week project
costing $100,000.
We're 40% complete and we've spent $60,000
so far, right?
So in a previous video, then,
we had determined what our
planned value and earned
value are going to be, right?
Our planned value,
remember, is how much work
we should have done at this point in time.
So if we're five weeks into a 10-week
project, we should have completed
five-tenths of the work, or 50% of the
work.
The entire work should be costing
$100,000.
So our planned value would be $50,000.
Our earned value, right,
again, for in a previous
video, it says here that
we're 40% complete.
That's what we've actually accomplished.
Earned value is what we've actually
accomplished.
So it says here we're 40% complete.
We have actually done 40% of the $100,000
worth of work.
And so our own value is $40,000.
So if I just put this into
another little scenario,
so think of this project
as building a road.
So we're building a road that's going to
cost $100,000.
And it's going to take us 10 weeks to
build this road.
So each week we are going to complete one
tenth of the work.
We're going to build this road in 10
sections.
And each section is going to take us one
week, so it's a 10 week project.
And so each section of the road is going
to cost us $10,000.
So 10 sections, 10 weeks, $100,000.
So if we are five weeks
into this project, then
we should have built
five sections of the road.
Because each week we are planning to build
one section.
So five weeks, we should have built five
sections of the road.
of the road.
But let's say we've only built four
sections of the road.
What does that tell us about our project?
We are behind schedule, right?
So if we've built, if we are supposed to
build five sections of the road,
then we should have spent $50,000 up to
that point.
We should have done $50,000 worth of work
up to that point.
But we've only done 40% of the work.
We've only built four sections of the
road.
So we've only done $40,000 worth of work.
What does that tell us?
It tells us we're behind schedule.
And if you look at these two numbers,
we're behind schedule by how much?
$10,000.
And that is schedule variance,
right?
That is what schedule variance means.
Now, the official formula for schedule
variance is earned value
minus planned value.
So our earned value is 40,000.
Planned value is 50,000.
So a scheduled variance in this case is
negative $10,000.
So understanding the terms.
understand the terms that's a key earned
value is what we've actually accomplished
we've accomplished 40,000 planned value is
what we should have accomplished 50,000
that's what we should have done so the
difference then is how much ahead of
schedule or behind schedule we are in this
case we're behind schedule by 10,000 right
and that negative means that we're behind
schedule and that's very important as well
if it was positive it would
mean we're ahead of
schedule now 10 $10,000
happens to be one week, right?
10 weeks project costing
$100,000 so we should
be doing $10,000 worth of work per week.
So 10,000 actually happens to be one week.
So you could also say we're a week behind
schedule, right?
However, for the purpose of
earned value management,
right, you will not say we're
a week behind schedule.
You'll always say we are $10,000 worth of
work behind schedule.
All right.
So always remember that.
it's always in terms of a dollar value.
Right.
So negative means where
we're behind schedule, as in this
case, positive 10,000 would
mean that we're ahead of schedule.
Of course, in the exam, remember,
they would give you both options.
They might say negative $10,000 or
positive $10,000.
They both have two different meanings.
So make sure you
understand again what these
terms mean, what the
negative and positive means.
Okay.
Now, that was schedule variance.
Let's talk about cost variance,
right?
Now, we have done $40,000 worth of work,
We're 40% complete.
That's what we've actually accomplished,
right?
We've built four sections of the road.
And so in building four sections of the
road, we should have spent $40,000.
But our actual cost, given to us in the
question, says that we've
actually spent $60,000.
So what does that tell you about whole
project?
It tells us we're over budget.
Tells us we've overspent.
By how much?
$20,000.
What have we just calculated there?
We've calculated another formula.
We've calculated a term called cost
variance.
So, official formula for cost variance is
earned value minus actual cost.
But again, just understand what it means.
If you understand what it
means, it's going to be so
much easier to answer
any of these math questions.
Right.
So cost variance, how much over budget or
under budget?
That's what cost variance is.
How much over budget or under budget that
we are at this point in time.
Right, we have done $40,000 worth of work.
So we should have spent $40,000.
We've actually spent $60,000.
So our cost variance is negative $20,000.
Okay.